‎SAY NO TO PIRACY, SUPPORT ORIGINALS
قل لا للقرصنة، ادعم الأعمال الأصلية
‎ADAPTED FROM XI XING’S NOVEL ‎QUEEN CHU‎ ON QIDIAN.COM
مقتبس من رواية شي شينغ "الملكة تشو" على موقع QIDIAN.COM
The Emperor passed away!
توفي الإمبراطور!
The Anping Rebellion came to an end.
انتهى تمرد أنبينغ.
In this life, I cut off Xiao Xun's path to the throne.
في هذه الحياة، قطعتُ طريق شياو شون إلى العرش.
But this game to crush him has just begun.
لكن هذه اللعبة لسحقه قد بدأت للتو.
Your Highness, congratulations on getting what you want.
صاحب السمو، أهنئكم على حصولكم على ما تريدون.
The same to you, Grand Mentor Deng.
وأنت كذلك يا كبير المعلمين دينغ.
DENG YI, THE GRAND MENTOR
دينغ يي، المرشد الكبير
You got wealth and honor as you had longed for.
لقد نلتَ الثروة والشرف كما كنتَ تتوق إليهما.
The Imperial Guard Commander was involved
كان قائد الحرس الإمبراطوري متورطًا
and executed.
وتم تنفيذه.
This position
هذا المنصب
concerns the entire imperial city and even the royal clan.
الأمر يتعلق بالمدينة الإمبراطورية بأكملها وحتى بالعشيرة الملكية.
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
Anyone in mind?
هل هناك من يخطر ببالك؟
Jiu.
جيو.
Your Highness,
صاحب السمو،
what do you mean?
ماذا تقصد؟
This is my first order.
هذا طلبي الأول.
Fu Jiu, retainer of the Chu Clan,
فو جيو، أحد أتباع عشيرة تشو،
will be promoted to the Imperial Guard Commander.
سيتم ترقيته إلى رتبة قائد الحرس الإمبراطوري.
He can be armed at court.
يمكن أن يكون مسلحاً في المحكمة.
Any objection, Grand Mentor?
هل لديك أي اعتراض، أيها المرشد الأكبر؟
IMPERIAL GUARD
الحرس الإمبراطوري
Don't regret it.
لا تندم على ذلك.
Don't make me regret it.
لا تجعلني أندم على ذلك.
General! Urgent message from the Capital!
أيها الجنرال! رسالة عاجلة من العاصمة!
Urgent message from the Capital!
رسالة عاجلة من العاصمة!
General!
عام!
General, message from the Capital!
يا جنرال، رسالة من العاصمة!
THE EMPEROR IS DEAD. HIS FINAL EDICT NAMES CHU ZHAO AS
مات الإمبراطور. وصيته الأخيرة تُسمّي تشو تشاو
GRAND PRINCESS, TO CO-RULE WITH THE GRAND MENTOR
الأميرة الكبرى، لتشارك الحكم مع المرشد الكبير
His Majesty has died. Zhao…
توفي جلالته. تشاو...
She's the Grand Princess now.
هي الآن الأميرة الكبرى.
What on earth has she gone through?
ما الذي مرت به يا ترى؟
Complicated infighting in the court
صراعات داخلية معقدة في المحكمة
is far more fierce than that on the frontier.
إنها أشد ضراوة بكثير من تلك الموجودة على الحدود.
At least, she's safe now.
على الأقل، هي بأمان الآن.
Glad she's safe.
الحمد لله أنها بخير.
General, enemies are invading!
أيها الجنرال، الأعداء يغزون!
Arm up! Move out!
استعدوا! انطلقوا!
TAIJI HALL
قاعة تايجي
His Majesty has arrived.
لقد وصل جلالته.
Zhao.
تشاو.
I want Zhao to be here.
أريد أن يكون تشاو هنا.
XIAO XUN, HEIR TO THE LORD OF XIAONAN
شياو شون، وريث لورد شياونان
XIE YANFANG, THE PRIME MINISTER
شيه يانفانج، رئيس الوزراء
DENG YI, THE GRAND MENTOR
دينغ يي، المرشد الكبير
Your Majesty,
جلالة الملك،
this is inappropriate.
هذا غير لائق.
Yeah, Your Majesty.
نعم، يا صاحب الجلالة.
There is no precedent.
لا يوجد سابقة.
Let the Grand Princess enter.
فلتدخل الأميرة الكبرى.
Yu, what's wrong?
يو، ما الخطب؟
Zhao, I don't want to walk alone.
تشاو، لا أريد أن أسير وحدي.
You walk with me, all right?
ستسير معي، حسناً؟
If a woman interferes with politics, the state will collapse.
إذا تدخلت امرأة في السياسة، ستنهار الدولة.
Please behave, Your Highness.
يرجى التحلي بالأدب يا صاحب السمو.
Chamberlain, don't you remember what happened before?
تشامبرلين، ألا تتذكر ما حدث من قبل؟
When Dowager Empress Xie ruled behind the curtain,
عندما حكمت الإمبراطورة الأرملة شي من وراء الستار،
you were the first to urge the emperor to take the throne.
كنت أول من حث الإمبراطور على تولي العرش.
Your Majesty, time to move on.
جلالتكم، حان وقت الرحيل.
DILIGENT AND VIRTUOUS
مجتهد وفاضل
Kneel.
اركع.
Your Majesty, may you have longevity
جلالتكم، أدعو الله أن يطيل في عمركم
and a prosperous reign!
وحكم مزدهر!
Rise.
يعلو.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
شكراً لك يا صاحب الجلالة.
Mr. Xie, still here?
السيد شي، هل ما زلت هنا؟
I've lingered for a moment
لقد ترددت للحظة
to thank you on His Majesty's behalf.
لأشكركم نيابة عن جلالة الملك.
It's so polite of you, Mr. Xie.
هذا لطف كبير منك يا سيد شي.
I don't know how I should reply.
لا أعرف كيف يجب أن أرد.
You're from the direct line of the Xie Clan of Gaoyang.
أنت من السلالة المباشرة لعشيرة شي من غاويانغ.
And by blood, you're Yu's uncle.
وبالدم، أنت عم يو.
You can call him by his nickname in private.
يمكنك مناداته بلقبه على انفراد.
Then let me thank you, Your Highness,
إذن اسمح لي أن أشكرك يا صاحب السمو.
on behalf of my clan, for saving Yu's life
نيابة عن عشيرتي، لإنقاذ حياة يو
and keeping his throne.
والحفاظ على عرشه.
You flatter me, Mr. Xie.
أنت تبالغ في مدحي يا سيد شي.
Yu and I will rely on you and your clan.
سنعتمد أنا ويو عليك وعلى عشيرتك.
You're modest, Your Highness.
أنت متواضع يا صاحب السمو.
I know it perfectly well.
أعرف ذلك جيداً.
You didn't get where you are by relying on my clan.
لم تصل إلى ما أنت عليه بالاعتماد على عشيرتي.
Instead, my clan relied on you.
بدلاً من ذلك، اعتمدت عشيرتي عليك.
Otherwise,
خلاف ذلك،
I wouldn't have had a position in the court.
لم يكن لي منصب في المحكمة.
Since we're in the same boat, forget about the formalities.
بما أننا في نفس الموقف، فلننسَ الإجراءات الرسمية.
When we're outside the court, I'll call you Yanfang. All right?
عندما نكون خارج الملعب، سأناديك يانفانغ. حسناً؟
It's my honor.
إنه لشرف لي.
After you come back here,
بعد عودتك إلى هنا،
you look very well.
تبدو بصحة جيدة جداً.
I wonder what illness
أتساءل ما هو المرض
made you leave the Capital for a long recovery.
أجبرك ذلك على مغادرة العاصمة لفترة نقاهة طويلة.
A long-standing illness.
مرض مزمن.
Thank you for your concern.
شكراً لاهتمامكم.
In the previous life, he was best at disguising.
في حياته السابقة، كان بارعاً في التنكر.
His clan had a century-long history with profound impact.
لعشيرته تاريخ يمتد لقرن من الزمان مع تأثير عميق.
To put Xiao Xun off his guard,
لإبعاد انتباه شياو شون،
he feigned illness and stayed in Gaoyang.
تظاهر بالمرض وبقي في غاويانغ.
But he secretly gathered private troops and expanded his power.
لكنه جمع سراً قوات خاصة ووسع نفوذه.
A man like him, who keeps a low profile,
رجل مثله، يفضل البقاء بعيدًا عن الأنظار،
is more likely to have the last laugh.
من المرجح أن يكون له الكلمة الأخيرة.
Why do you stare at me like that?
لماذا تحدق بي هكذا؟
Am I untidily dressed?
هل ملابسي غير مرتبة؟
I was just thinking…
كنت أفكر للتو...
Yanfang, you're an extraordinary young man.
يانفانغ، أنت شاب استثنائي.
Among all the ministers,
من بين جميع الوزراء،
I've never seen anyone who could be even half as smart as you.
لم أرَ قط شخصاً يتمتع بنصف ذكائك.
I wonder how sincere you are
أتساءل عن مدى صدقك
when you praise me.
عندما تمدحني.
Every word I say is sincere.
كل كلمة أقولها صادقة.
You're a master strategist.
أنت خبير استراتيجي بارع.
I'm waiting for you to advise me on what the Lord of Xiaonan will do next.
أنتظر منك أن تنصحني بما سيفعله سيد شياونان لاحقاً.
The Lord of Xiaonan didn't mourn the late Emperor
لم يحزن سيد شياونان على الإمبراطور الراحل
or pay homage to the new emperor.
أو تقديم فروض الولاء للإمبراطور الجديد.
His ambition is all too evident.
طموحه واضح للغاية.
The Grand Mentor has sent nearby troops to Xiaonan Prefecture secretly
أرسل المرشد الأعظم قوات قريبة إلى محافظة شياونان سراً.
in the name of hunting remnants of the rebels.
باسم مطاردة فلول المتمردين.
The Lord of Xiaonan has schemed for over two decades.
لقد دبر سيد شياونان المكائد لأكثر من عقدين من الزمن.
I'm afraid a lot of things are no longer under the court's control.
أخشى أن الكثير من الأمور لم تعد تحت سيطرة المحكمة.
Can't we strike first?
ألا يمكننا أن نبادر بالهجوم؟
Not until we have a just reason.
لن نفعل ذلك إلا إذا كان لدينا سبب وجيه.
The Lord of Xiaonan declared he was overwhelmed with grief
أعلن سيد شياونان أنه غارق في الحزن
and bedridden over the late Emperor's death.
ولزم الفراش حزناً على وفاة الإمبراطور الراحل.
So, he couldn't come here.
لذا، لم يستطع المجيء إلى هنا.
And Yu is his junior.
ويو هو أصغر منه سناً.
We must placate him.
يجب علينا استرضاءه.
What's worse,
والأسوأ من ذلك،
foes from the Northern Desert are lurking on the frontier.
يتربص الأعداء القادمون من الصحراء الشمالية على الحدود.
New court, young emperor. Internal and external troubles.
بلاط جديد، إمبراطور شاب. مشاكل داخلية وخارجية.
Our state is too fragile to survive unrest.
دولتنا هشة للغاية بحيث لا يمكنها الصمود أمام الاضطرابات.
That's why the late Emperor's edict stated
ولهذا السبب نص مرسوم الإمبراطور الراحل
Xiao Xun made contributions in saving the throne.
ساهم شياو شون في إنقاذ العرش.
Otherwise, his father might have an excuse for rebellion.
وإلا، فقد يكون لدى والده عذر للتمرد.
But actually, Xiao Xun is the mastermind behind this.
لكن في الحقيقة، شياو شون هو العقل المدبر وراء هذا.
He set up the trap to kill the Crown Prince and Princess.
لقد نصب الفخ لقتل ولي العهد والأميرة.
The Crown Princess is my eldest sister.
الأميرة ولية العهد هي أختي الكبرى.
She's like my mother.
إنها مثل أمي.
I'm the mortal enemy of Xiao Xun and his father.
أنا العدو اللدود لشياو شون ووالده.
One day, I'll kill them with my own hands
يوماً ما، سأقتلهم بيدي
to avenge my sister.
للانتقام لأختي.
But not now.
لكن ليس الآن.
Xiao Xun appears to be the imperial uncle.
يبدو أن شياو شون هو العم الإمبراطوري.
But actually, he's still a hostage.
لكن في الحقيقة، ما زال رهينة.
Don't worry, Your Highness. Take everything slowly.
لا تقلق يا صاحب السمو. خذ الأمور ببطء.
Do not rush things.
لا تستعجل الأمور.
I understand.
أفهم.
Thank you for your instructions.
شكراً لتوجيهاتكم.
If you have any further confusion, summon me anytime.
إذا كان لديك أي استفسار آخر، فاتصل بي في أي وقت.
Be careful.
احرص.
The paths in this palace
الممرات في هذا القصر
are treacherous.
غادرة.
So, someone like Xie Yanfang, upright and noble,
لذا، شخص مثل شيه يانفانغ، مستقيم ونبيل،
also wants to kill people out of hatred.
يريد أيضاً قتل الناس بدافع الكراهية.
Since you also intend to oppose Xiao Xun,
بما أنك تنوي أيضاً معارضة شياو شون،
then don't blame me for taking advantage of you.
إذاً لا تلومني على استغلالك.
The Xie Clan of Gaoyang came to rescue with 5,000 private troops.
عائلة شي من غاويانغ جاءت لإنقاذهم بخمسة آلاف جندي من القوات الخاصة.
It's him.
إنه هو.
The Xie Clan.
عشيرة شيه.
We heard your mother worked in a brothel.
سمعنا أن والدتك كانت تعمل في بيت دعارة.
Our clan doesn't want dirty people.
عشيرتنا لا تريد أشخاصاً قذرين.
Since you're just like your mother,
بما أنك تشبه والدتك تماماً،
how about we pierce your ear
ما رأيك أن نثقب أذنك؟
and dress you up?
وهل سألبسك؟
Maybe you'll fetch a good price.
ربما ستحصل على سعر جيد.
You can endure a lot. One more.
يمكنك تحمل الكثير. واحد آخر.
Stop.
قف.
Uncle, it's really kind of you.
يا عمي، هذا لطف منك حقاً.
You even pity an illegitimate child.
بل إنك تشفق حتى على طفل غير شرعي.
Xie Xiao, you and your peers bullied the weak boy.
شي شياو، أنت ورفاقك تنمرتم على الصبي الضعيف.
Do you know how you should be punished?
هل تعرف كيف يجب أن تُعاقب؟
Do you want me to take you to the ancestral hall
هل تريدني أن آخذك إلى قاعة الأجداد؟
and make you kneel?
ويجعلك تركع؟
Uncle, we're wrong. We'll leave now.
يا عمي، نحن مخطئون. سنرحل الآن.
It hurts, huh? Go get some medicine.
يؤلمك، أليس كذلك؟ اذهب واحصل على بعض الأدوية.
No need.
لا حاجة.
Your ear…
أذنك…
Why do you wear that?
لماذا ترتدي هذا؟
-If people see it… -I'm not afraid of being seen.
-إذا رآه الناس... -أنا لست خائفاً من أن يراني أحد.
This will become part of my flesh and blood
سيصبح هذا جزءًا من لحمي ودمي
and remind me day after day not to forget
وذكّرني يوماً بعد يوم ألا أنسى
how they pierced
كيف قاموا بالثقب
my ear.
أذني.
And one day, they will be pierced by me.
وفي يوم من الأيام، سأقوم أنا بثقبها.
How dare you rebel?
كيف تجرؤ على التمرد؟
Your whole clan may be executed!
قد يتم إعدام عشيرتك بأكملها!
That's just what I want.
هذا بالضبط ما أريده.
Congrats, Yanlai.
مبروك يا يانلاي.
With the Commander's token,
باستخدام رمز القائد،
you look impressive.
تبدو مثيراً للإعجاب.
The Grand Princess
الأميرة الكبرى
isn't as weak as you think she is.
ليست ضعيفة كما تظن.
She's indeed extraordinary.
إنها حقاً استثنائية.
You worked for Chu Ling for so many years.
لقد عملتَ لدى تشو لينغ لسنوات عديدة.
You know more about Miss Chu than I do.
أنت تعرف عن الآنسة تشو أكثر مما أعرف.
She acted perfectly.
لقد تصرفت بشكل مثالي.
But sadly, she's way too impatient.
لكن للأسف، إنها متسرعة للغاية.
I'm quite curious.
أنا فضولي للغاية.
Why did she suddenly hate Xiao Xun?
لماذا كرهت شياو شون فجأة؟
How did this engaged couple become estranged?
كيف انفصل هذان الخطيبان؟
Why can't they get along?
لماذا لا يستطيعون التفاهم؟
From the very beginning,
منذ البداية،
Xiao Xun wasn't after Chu Zhao,
لم يكن شياو شون يطارد تشو تشاو،
but the frontier troops under Chu Ling's control.
لكن قوات الحدود كانت تحت سيطرة تشو لينغ.
She would notice it if she weren't a fool.
كانت ستلاحظ ذلك لو لم تكن حمقاء.
It sounds like…
يبدو الأمر وكأنه...
Yanlai, you think she's clever.
يانلاي، هل تعتقد أنها ذكية؟
I've never heard you praise anyone else like that.
لم أسمعك من قبل تمدح أي شخص آخر بهذه الطريقة.
The way you look at her…
الطريقة التي تنظر بها إليها...
It's like how you look at your pet.
يشبه الأمر نظرتك إلى حيوانك الأليف.
However,
لكن،
she's a wolf growing up in the desert.
إنها ذئبة نشأت في الصحراء.
If you're careless,
إذا كنت مهملاً،
she'll bite through your neck.
ستعض رقبتك.
What's bad about a biting wolf?
ما هو السيء في الذئب العاض؟
Isn't that funnier than a dog wagging its tail?
أليس هذا أطرف من كلب يهز ذيله؟
Yanlai, you know that.
يانلاي، أنت تعلم ذلك.
I always like clever people.
أنا دائماً معجب بالأشخاص الأذكياء.
I've made my point.
لقد أوضحت وجهة نظري.
Young Master Xie, be careful not to get burned.
يا سيد شيه الشاب، احذر من أن تحترق.
Thank you for your concern.
شكراً لاهتمامكم.
When you have time,
عندما يتوفر لديك الوقت،
come back home.
عد إلى المنزل.
After all,
في النهاية،
you're a Xie.
أنت من عائلة شي.
XIE
شي
XIE YANLAI, THE IMPERIAL GUARD COMMANDER
شي يانلاي، قائد الحرس الإمبراطوري
Now you know
الآن أنت تعرف
why the Imperial Guard Tally can't be given to Fu Jiu.
لماذا لا يمكن إعطاء إحصاء الحرس الإمبراطوري إلى فو جيو؟
He's a Xie. He's the ninth child of the Xie Family,
هو من عائلة شي. إنه الطفل التاسع في عائلة شي.
Xie Yanlai.
شيه يانلاي.
I know.
أنا أعرف.
You know?
أنت تعرف؟
He worked for my father for five years under a false name.
لقد عمل لدى والدي لمدة خمس سنوات تحت اسم مستعار.
How could he not be exposed?
كيف لا يُكشف أمره؟
You think my father's troops didn't know his identity?
أتظن أن جنود والدي لم يكونوا يعرفون هويته؟
They did. They just didn't care.
لقد فعلوا ذلك. لكنهم لم يكترثوا.
Whether he's Fu Jiu or Xie Yanlai,
سواء كان فو جيو أو شي يانلاي،
if he had ill intentions or harmed frontier troops,
إذا كانت لديه نوايا سيئة أو ألحق الضرر بقوات الحدود،
my father would punish him accordingly.
سيعاقبه والدي وفقاً لذلك.
But you gave the Tally to someone from the Xie Clan.
لكنك أعطيت الإحصاء لشخص من عشيرة شي.
Do you know what that means?
هل تعرف ماذا يعني ذلك؟
Calm down, Grand Mentor.
اهدأ يا مرشدنا الكبير.
I can give you more.
بإمكاني أن أعطيك المزيد.
Seven shops in Yongfeng Alley will be put under your name tomorrow.
سيتم تسجيل سبعة متاجر في زقاق يونغفنغ باسمك غداً.
Glazed cups and glowing pearls aren't rare.
الأكواب المزججة واللآلئ المتوهجة ليست نادرة.
Two boxes have been sent to you.
تم إرسال صندوقين إليك.
Feel free to enjoy them.
استمتع بها بحرية.
If you need anything else, don't hesitate to tell me.
إذا احتجت إلى أي شيء آخر، فلا تتردد في إخباري.
I'll do my best to get it for you.
سأبذل قصارى جهدي لأحصل عليه لك.
Why, Your Highness?
لماذا يا صاحب السمو؟
Do you know why the palace walls can stand for a century?
هل تعلم لماذا يمكن لأسوار القصر أن تصمد لمدة قرن؟
Because every brick stays where it belongs.
لأن كل لبنة تبقى في مكانها الصحيح.
I made Xie Yanlai the Imperial Guard Commander.
لقد جعلتُ شي يانلاي قائد الحرس الإمبراطوري.
But I'll count on you for court affairs.
لكنني سأعتمد عليك في شؤون المحكمة.
So rest assured, Mr. Deng.
لذا اطمئن يا سيد دينغ.
Before I'm no longer the princess,
قبل أن أتوقف عن كوني الأميرة،
your position will be rock-solid.
سيكون موقفك راسخاً كالصخر.
I will
أنا سوف
spare no effort.
لا تدخر جهدا.
I've heard your mother
لقد سمعت والدتك
has been missing the hometown.
كان يشتاق إلى مسقط رأسه.
So I sent men at full gallop to bring some millet from your hometown.
لذلك أرسلت رجالاً يركضون بأقصى سرعة لجلب بعض الدخن من مسقط رأسك.
It's nothing.
لا شئ.
Hearing you're a very good son,
سمعت أنك ابن بار جداً،
I'm just offering a little present.
أنا فقط أقدم هدية صغيرة.
I… Thank you for your consideration.
أشكركم على اهتمامكم.
Everyone has his weakness.
لكل شخص نقاط ضعفه.
So do you, Deng Yi.
وأنت كذلك يا دينغ يي.
Xie Yanfang is famous throughout the state.
تشتهر شي يانفانغ في جميع أنحاء الولاية.
But he still can't resist flattery.
لكنه لا يزال لا يستطيع مقاومة الإطراء.
Since he likes obedient people,
لأنه يحب الأشخاص المطيعين،
I'll sheathe my claws before him.
سأغمد مخالبي قبل أن أراه.
As for Deng Yi…
أما بالنسبة لدينغ يي ...
He's greedy and filial to his mother.
إنه جشع وبرٌّ بأمه.
I'll just give him what he wants.
سأعطيه ما يريد.
Xie Yanlai.
شيه يانلاي.
All the ministers are fierce.
جميع الوزراء شرسون.
He's the only one…
هو الوحيد...
who protects me with his own life.
الذي يحميني بحياته.
XIE YANLAI
شيه يانلاي
Jiu.
جيو.
I can trust you…
أستطيع أن أثق بك...
right?
يمين؟
Beat him!
اهزمه!
How dare you, an illegitimate son,
كيف تجرؤ يا ابن غير شرعي؟
burn the ancestors' tablets?
هل نحرق ألواح الأجداد؟
You even angered your father to death.
بل إنك أغضبت والدك حتى الموت.
Believe it or not,
صدق أو لا تصدق،
I'll dig your mother out and feed her to the dogs.
سأحفر قبر والدتك وأطعمها للكلاب.
Lowborn! You bring bad luck.
يا وضيع! أنت تجلب الحظ السيئ.
Pah!
هه!
Lowborn! Kill him!
يا وضيع! اقتله!
Hit him hard!
اضربه بقوة!
Beat him to death!
اضربوه حتى الموت!
What is he doing?
ماذا يفعل؟
Are you killing Yanlai, Great-uncle?
هل تقتل يانلاي يا عمي الكبير؟
Father has just died.
توفي والدي للتو.
Do you want to lose another family member?
هل تريد أن تفقد فرداً آخر من عائلتك؟
But he burned the ancestral hall.
لكنه أحرق قاعة الأجداد.
-Right! -Without descendants,
- صحيح! - بدون ذرية،
what do we need the hall for?
لماذا نحتاج إلى القاعة؟
By killing a Xie descendant,
بقتل أحد أحفاد شي،
will you answer to our ancestors?
هل ستُحاسب أمام أسلافنا؟
‎HONOR THE CLAN, UNITE THE KIN
أكرموا العشيرة، ووحدوا الروابط الأسرية
Yanlai.
يانلاي.
In childhood, you were afraid of pain.
في طفولتك، كنت تخاف من الألم.
You cried in the barn for an hour over your scraped knee.
بكيتِ في الحظيرة لمدة ساعة كاملة فوق ركبتكِ المجروحة.
But today, you endured 18 lashes. Like a different person.
لكنك اليوم تحملت 18 جلدة. وكأنك شخص آخر.
I'm Fu Jiu.
أنا فو جيو.
I'm not your brother.
أنا لست أخاك.
I remember, when you were ten,
أتذكر، عندما كنت في العاشرة من عمرك،
you stole my books to pad the manger.
لقد سرقت كتبي لتكدس المال في المذود.
I chased to the west yard
طاردتُ إلى الفناء الغربي
and saw you wrapping a crippled dog in the doghouse.
ورأيتك تلف كلباً معاقاً في بيت الكلب.
At that time, you said everything had a soul.
في ذلك الوقت، قلتَ إن لكل شيء روح.
A crippled dog shouldn't be discarded.
لا ينبغي التخلص من كلب معاق.
But now, what's going on?
لكن ماذا يحدث الآن؟
When you're discarded,
عندما يتم التخلي عنك،
why do you let their words get to you?
لماذا تسمح لكلماتهم بالتأثير عليك؟
You're just like them!
أنت مثلهم تماماً!
You look down on my mother and me.
أنت تنظر بازدراء إلى أمي وإليّ.
Why are you pretending to be a caring brother?
لماذا تتظاهر بأنك أخ حنون؟
I am your elder brother.
أنا أخوك الأكبر.
I don't need to pretend.
لست بحاجة للتظاهر.
‎XIE
شي
Jiu, you haven't fully recovered. Why are you on night duty?
جيو، لم تتعافَ تماماً. لماذا أنت في نوبة العمل الليلية؟
It's not appropriate for you to come so late.
ليس من المناسب أن تأتي متأخراً هكذا.
I'm just here to give you a cloak.
أنا هنا فقط لأعطيك عباءة.
You won't reject it, will you?
لن ترفضه، أليس كذلك؟
I'm used to cotton.
أنا معتاد على القطن.
I won't like
لن يعجبني
fancy fabrics.
أقمشة فاخرة.
Cotton is too soft to guard against arrows.
القطن ناعم جداً بحيث لا يمكنه الحماية من السهام.
Don't you agree?
ألا توافق؟
Mr. Xie Yanlai.
السيد شيه يانلاي.
Your Highness, are you testing me
يا صاحب السمو، هل تختبرني؟
or trying to win me over?
أم أنك تحاول كسب ودّي؟
I heard when you served under my father,
سمعت أنك خدمت تحت قيادة والدي،
you didn't bat an eye when breaking through ranks
لم يرف لك جفن وأنت تشق طريقك عبر الرتب
and pulled down the flag.
ثم أنزل العلم.
But now,
لكن الآن،
why are you afraid of a cloak?
لماذا تخاف من الرداء؟
Afraid?
خائف؟
Now I have the Imperial Guard Tally.
الآن لديّ إحصاء الحرس الإمبراطوري.
Shouldn't you
ألا ينبغي عليك
be the one who is afraid?
هل أكون أنا الخائف؟
I am afraid.
أنا خائف.
Covert schemes are harder to dodge
يصعب تفادي المخططات السرية
than open attacks on the frontier.
بدلاً من شن هجمات مفتوحة على الحدود.
So, Mr. Xie, will you consider
إذن، سيد شيه، هل ستنظر في الأمر؟
becoming my ally?
هل ستصبح حليفًا لي؟
Now, you know who I am.
الآن، أنت تعرف من أنا.
Why do you think I'll pick your side
لماذا تعتقد أنني سأختار جانبك؟
instead of my own clan?
بدلاً من عشيرتي؟
Because I'll prove to you
لأنني سأثبت لك ذلك
I'm more worthy of your support than Xie Yanfang.
أنا أستحق دعمكم أكثر من شي يانفانغ.
Is this a deal or an order?
هل هذا اتفاق أم أمر؟
It is a request.
إنه طلب.
Your Highness,
صاحب السمو،
you're powerful now.
أنت الآن قوي.
Your request is too much for me.
طلبك يفوق طاقتي.
Let alone the support thing.
ناهيك عن مسألة الدعم.
You'd better
من الأفضل لك
take the cloak back.
خذ الرداء.
Life is like a chess game. Nothing is set yet.
الحياة أشبه بلعبة الشطرنج. لم يتم تحديد أي شيء بعد.
Jiu, it's a little rash of you to reject me so firmly.
جيو، من التهور بعض الشيء أن ترفضني بهذه القسوة.
If one day, you change your mind,
إذا غيرت رأيك يوماً ما،
come to me anytime.
تعال إليّ في أي وقت.
Congratulations.
تهانينا.
You've become the Grand Princess and gained the supreme power.
لقد أصبحتِ الأميرة الكبرى وحصلتِ على السلطة العليا.
You can finally take revenge.
يمكنك الآن الانتقام.
No.
لا.
I want more than that.
أريد أكثر من ذلك.
Don't you remember how Xiao Xun strangled you,
ألا تتذكر كيف خنقك شياو شون؟
how he cut off your father's head,
كيف قطع رأس والدك،
and how he annihilated your clan?
وكيف أباد عشيرتك؟
Even if you have to lose your life,
حتى لو كان ذلك يعني فقدان حياتك،
you should make Xiao Xun pay blood for blood!
يجب أن تجعل شياو شون يدفع ثمن دمه بالدم!
Nothing but hatred can get you up to the peak of power.
لا شيء سوى الكراهية يمكن أن يوصلك إلى قمة السلطة.
can make you use everyone,
يمكن أن يدفعك إلى استغلال الجميع.
especially men.
وخاصة الرجال.
They're greedy for power and beautiful women.
إنهم متعطشون للسلطة والنساء الجميلات.
If you don't mind,
إن لم يكن لديك مانع،
they will do anything for you.
سيفعلون أي شيء من أجلك.
By then, you'll be able to take revenge without bloodshed.
حينها، ستكون قادراً على الانتقام دون إراقة دماء.
Revenge.
انتقام.
That's not my only desire.
ليست هذه رغبتي الوحيدة.
I do hate Xiao Xun.
أنا أكره شياو شون.
I also want to cut off his path to success
أريد أيضاً أن أقطع طريقه نحو النجاح
and ruin everything he longs for.
ويدمر كل ما يتوق إليه.
To make all this happen,
لتحقيق كل هذا،
I have to hide my abilities
عليّ أن أخفي قدراتي
and conceal my edge for further action.
وأخفي سلاحي استعداداً لأي إجراء لاحق.
With everything you have now?
بكل ما تملكه الآن؟
You're a princess in name only.
أنتِ أميرة بالاسم فقط.
Xiao Xun is the imperial uncle.
شياو شون هو العم الإمبراطوري.
Deng Yi oversees the court.
يشرف دينغ يي على المحكمة.
The Xie Clan has accumulated merit.
لقد اكتسبت عشيرة شيه جدارة كبيرة.
What do you have?
ماذا لديك؟
What makes you think you can fight them?
ما الذي يجعلك تعتقد أنك تستطيع محاربتهم؟
Didn't you risk your life to become the Grand Princess
ألم تخاطري بحياتك لتصبحي الأميرة الكبرى؟
just because you wanted Xiao Xun to regret it
لمجرد أنك أردت أن يندم شياو شون على ذلك
and wanted to slice him by the blade of power?
وأراد أن يقطعه بشفرة القوة؟
No.
لا.
I want more than this.
أريد أكثر من هذا.
I want to rule behind the curtain.
أريد أن أحكم من وراء الكواليس.
I want the real power.
أريد السلطة الحقيقية.
I'll make my father and me
سأجعلني أنا وأبي
live a long life.
أتمنى لك عمراً مديداً.
What I want is…
ما أريده هو...
Fate won't repeat itself.
لن يتكرر القدر.
What?
ماذا؟
Yeah.
نعم.
The Grand Princess is here.
الأميرة الكبرى هنا.
That's utterly improper.
هذا أمر غير لائق على الإطلاق.
It has never happened before.
لم يحدث هذا من قبل.
Indeed.
بالفعل.
Your Highness, it was all right
سموكم، كان الأمر على ما يرام
that you attended the enthronement ceremony.
أنك حضرت حفل التتويج.
But now, how can you even attend court?
لكن الآن، كيف يمكنك حتى حضور المحكمة؟
Are you trying to rule behind the curtain
هل تحاول أن تحكم من وراء الكواليس؟
just like Dowager Empress Xie?
تمامًا مثل الإمبراطورة الأرملة شي؟
That's right.
هذا صحيح.
This is ridiculous.
هذا أمر سخيف.
Outrageous, indeed.
أمرٌ شائنٌ حقاً.
Who does she think she is?
من تظن نفسها؟
Come on.
تعال.
Ministers, my duty is to oversee the court.
أيها الوزراء، واجبي هو الإشراف على المحكمة.
His Majesty will rule sooner or later.
سيحكم جلالته عاجلاً أم آجلاً.
His Majesty should attend court.
ينبغي على جلالته حضور المحكمة.
Who made the rule that Your Highness can attend court?
من الذي وضع القاعدة التي تسمح لسموكم بحضور المحكمة؟
Good question, Mr. Qin.
سؤال جيد يا سيد تشين.
A few days ago, you failed your duty.
قبل بضعة أيام، فشلت في أداء واجبك.
By law, you should have been executed.
بحسب القانون، كان ينبغي إعدامك.
On the pretext of your military merit, you were given a minor penalty.
بحجة جدارتك العسكرية، تم فرض عقوبة بسيطة عليك.
I also want to ask you. Who made that rule?
أريد أن أسألك أيضاً: من وضع هذا القانون؟
We've been sparing no effort for our state.
لم ندخر جهداً من أجل ولايتنا.
But now, in the court,
لكن الآن، في المحكمة،
a woman outside the royal clan
امرأة من خارج العائلة المالكة
takes charge of politics. Isn't that ridiculous?
يتولى زمام السياسة. أليس هذا أمراً سخيفاً؟
Yeah. That's outrageous.
نعم، هذا أمرٌ شائن.
That's right. That's absurd.
هذا صحيح. هذا أمر سخيف.
Chamberlain,
تشامبرلين،
you're the father-in-law of the Third Prince
أنت والد زوجة الأمير الثالث
who killed his elder brother.
الذي قتل شقيقه الأكبر.
If His Majesty hadn't shown mercy,
لو لم يُظهر جلالته الرحمة،
you wouldn't be standing here and ranting.
ما كنت لتقف هنا وتثرثر.
Instead of feeling grateful, you make things difficult.
بدلاً من الشعور بالامتنان، أنت تجعل الأمور صعبة.
Aren't you biting the hand that feeds you?
ألا تعض اليد التي تطعمك؟
It's perceptive of you, Mr. Deng.
هذا يدل على فطنتك يا سيد دينغ.
You've figured out everything about all the ministers.
لقد عرفت كل شيء عن جميع الوزراء.
How admirable.
يا له من أمر مثير للإعجاب.
Within only a few days, you've put in so much effort.
لقد بذلت جهداً كبيراً في غضون أيام قليلة فقط .
This is truly a blessing for this state.
هذا نعمة حقيقية لهذه الولاية.
When you assist His Majesty so well,
عندما تساعدون جلالته على هذا النحو الجيد،
our state will be peaceful.
ستنعم ولايتنا بالسلام.
Entrusted by the late Emperor,
بتكليف من الإمبراطور الراحل،
I dare not slack off in my duty.
لا أجرؤ على التهاون في أداء واجبي.
Mr. Xie, you used to be sick and away from court for years.
السيد شي، لقد كنت مريضاً وغائباً عن المحكمة لسنوات.
When you're back here,
عندما تعود إلى هنا،
you must have a lot of confusions.
لا بد أن لديك الكثير من الحيرة.
If you want to discuss anything with me,
إذا كنت ترغب في مناقشة أي شيء معي،
I'm always at your service.
أنا دائماً في خدمتكم.
Ministers, present your reports,
أيها الوزراء، قدموا تقاريركم.
or the court is dismissed.
أو يتم رفض الدعوى من قبل المحكمة.
But… This…
لكن... هذا...
How could she say that?
كيف تجرؤ على قول ذلك؟
What a breach of rules.
يا له من خرق للقواعد!
Who does she think she is?
من تظن نفسها؟
She has no right to say that.
ليس لها الحق في قول ذلك.
She oversteps her authority.
إنها تتجاوز صلاحياتها.
She… She's being presumptuous.
إنها... إنها تتصرف بتهور.
-Yeah. -Who would accept that?
- أجل. - من سيقبل بذلك؟
Yeah.
نعم.
Commander Xie.
القائد شيه.
Her Highness ordered!
أمرت صاحبة السمو!
Present your reports!
قدموا تقاريركم!
Or the court is dismissed!
أو يتم رفض الدعوى!
I… I have something to report.
لديّ... لديّ شيءٌ أودّ الإبلاغ عنه.
Recently, I dreamed that the late Emperor wept blood,
حلمت مؤخراً بأن الإمبراطور الراحل كان يبكي دماً.
yearning for temple rites.
التوق إلى طقوس المعبد.
The late Emperor should cry out to the current emperor.
ينبغي على الإمبراطور الراحل أن يصرخ في وجه الإمبراطور الحالي.
Why would a hostage like you say such things?
لماذا قد يقول رهينة مثلك مثل هذه الأشياء؟
In that case, Mr. Xiao must have
في هذه الحالة، لا بد أن السيد شياو قد
a close connection with the late Emperor because they're blood-related.
تربطهم علاقة وثيقة بالإمبراطور الراحل لأنهم من نفس العائلة.
But oddly enough…
لكن الغريب في الأمر...
Mr. Xiao,
السيد شياو،
why didn't you dream of the Crown Prince?
لماذا لم تحلمي بولي العهد؟
Does the late Emperor also think
هل يعتقد الإمبراطور الراحل أيضاً
your branch is closer to him than the Crown Prince?
هل فرعكم أقرب إليه من ولي العهد؟
So, last night, Grandfather appeared in Uncle's dream.
إذن، ظهر الجد في حلم العم الليلة الماضية.
He must have been angry with me.
لا بد أنه كان غاضباً مني.
In the past few days, he often came into my dreams,
في الأيام القليلة الماضية، كان يظهر في أحلامي كثيراً.
saying he would fly a kite with me.
قال إنه سيطير طائرة ورقية معي.
But last night, he didn't appear.
لكنه لم يظهر الليلة الماضية.
Yu.
يو.
Your Highness, what do you think we should do?
يا صاحب السمو، ما رأيك فيما يجب علينا فعله؟
Since His Majesty had dreams,
بما أن جلالته كان لديه أحلام،
Mr. Deng and Mr. Xie shall prepare for the sacrifice thing.
سيقوم السيد دينغ والسيد شيه بالتحضير لأمر التضحية.
We'll do our best.
سنبذل قصارى جهدنا.
It's so tiring to attend court.
حضور المحكمة أمر مرهق للغاية.
Can I not go tomorrow?
هل يمكنني عدم الذهاب غداً؟
Yu, an emperor must put the state first instead of complaining all the time.
يا يو، يجب على الإمبراطور أن يضع مصلحة الدولة أولاً بدلاً من التذمر طوال الوقت.
-Where's my Nine-ring Puzzle? -Back there.
- أين أحجية الحلقات التسع الخاصة بي؟ - هناك في الخلف.
Watch your step. Don't trip.
انتبه لخطواتك. لا تتعثر.
All right.
حسنًا.
Without requesting an audience, I came in here uninvited.
دخلت إلى هنا دون دعوة، دون أن أطلب مقابلة أحد .
Please forgive me, Your Highness.
أرجو أن تسامحني يا صاحب السمو.
You're Yu's close family.
أنتم من عائلة يو المقربة.
And now I'm his sister.
والآن أصبحت أخته.
You and I are close too.
أنا وأنت مقربان أيضاً.
You don't need to inform others before you visit Yu.
لا تحتاج إلى إبلاغ الآخرين قبل زيارتك ليو.
But now, he's the Emperor, after all.
لكن الآن، هو الإمبراطور في نهاية المطاف.
I hope you'll inform me next time,
أتمنى أن تُبلغني في المرة القادمة،
so that I can be prepared.
حتى أكون مستعداً.
I'll keep that in mind.
سأضع ذلك في اعتباري.
Yu.
يو.
-I'm your… -Uncle.
أنا عمك ...
Be careful.
احرص.
You brought a toy to today's court, didn't you?
أحضرت لعبة إلى المحكمة اليوم، أليس كذلك؟
It's just a Nine-ring Puzzle.
إنها مجرد أحجية ذات تسع حلقات.
Give it to me.
أعطني إياه.
I know I was wrong.
أعلم أنني كنت مخطئاً.
Never do it again.
لا تكرر ذلك أبداً.
Yu,
يو،
this is Mr. Xie Yanfang from the Xie Clan.
هذا السيد شي يانفانغ من عشيرة شي.
He's also your uncle.
هو أيضاً عمك.
Xie Yanfang?
شيه يان فانغ؟
Oh, the Third Uncle.
أوه، العم الثالث.
Yu,
يو،
I know you hate my clan and me.
أعلم أنك تكره عشيرتي وتكرهني.
We failed to protect your parents as well as you.
لقد فشلنا في حماية والديك وكذلك أنت.
So, I came here today to apologize to you.
لذا، جئت إلى هنا اليوم لأعتذر لكم.
From now on, I'll spare no effort
من الآن فصاعدًا، لن أدخر جهدًا
to keep you safe.
للحفاظ على سلامتك.
Yu, it's time for morning classes.
يو، حان وقت الحصص الصباحية.
Go wait for me in the study, will you?
اذهب وانتظرني في غرفة الدراسة، حسناً؟
He's a kid,
إنه طفل،
and it's normal that he doesn't know how to hide his emotions.
ومن الطبيعي أنه لا يعرف كيف يخفي مشاعره.
Don't bother to console me.
لا داعي لمواساتي.
We do feel sorry for the massacre of the Crown Prince's family.
نشعر بالأسف الشديد إزاء المذبحة التي طالت عائلة ولي العهد.
We arrived too late to protect them.
وصلنا متأخرين جداً لحمايتهم.
Yu harbors some resentment,
يكنّ يو بعض الاستياء،
and I understand.
وأنا أتفهم ذلك.
Yu is still young.
لا يزال يو صغيراً.
After such a tragedy, his temperament changed somewhat.
بعد هذه المأساة، تغير مزاجه إلى حد ما.
Later on, he'll get better.
سيتحسن لاحقاً.
Next time you come,
في المرة القادمة التي تأتي فيها،
bring him some toys, and that might cheer him up.
أحضر له بعض الألعاب، وقد يُسعده ذلك.
How rare.
يا له من أمر نادر.
The two of you match well in character.
أنتما متوافقان تماماً في الشخصية.
How enviable.
يا له من أمر مثير للحسد.
Yeah.
نعم.
Commander Xie is exceptionally brave.
القائد شي شجاع بشكل استثنائي.
I admire him a lot.
أنا معجب به كثيراً.
I'll count on him for the safety of the imperial palace.
سأعتمد عليه في حماية القصر الإمبراطوري.
You know Xie Yanfang is suspicious.
أنت تعلم أن شي يانفانغ مثير للريبة.
But in front of him, you pretended to think highly of me.
لكن أمامه، تظاهرت بأنك تُكنّ لي تقديراً كبيراً.
What were you up to?
ماذا كنت تفعل؟
You didn't deny it just now.
لم تنكر ذلك للتو.
So, you agreed that I was telling the truth.
إذن، وافقتَ على أنني كنت أقول الحقيقة.
Does it mean
هل يعني ذلك
you've accepted my offer?
هل قبلت عرضي؟
It's my duty to protect Your Highness.
من واجبي حماية صاحب السمو.
Not because of your offer.
ليس بسبب عرضك.
Then have you decided?
هل حسمت أمرك إذن؟
Once you're the Commander,
بمجرد أن تصبح القائد،
you won't go back to Yunzhong.
لن تعود إلى يونتشونغ.
I was a retainer of your family.
كنتُ أحد أتباع عائلتكم.
I don't care about that.
لا يهمني ذلك.
As for you, the Grand Princess,
أما أنتِ يا أميرة العالم،
there's really no turning back.
لا مجال للتراجع حقاً.
Is this
هذا هو
what you really want?
ماذا تريد حقاً؟
Xie Yanfang is the head of ministers.
شي يانفانغ هو رئيس الوزراء.
Deng Yi controls speech.
يتحكم دينغ يي في الكلام.
Xiao Xun owns Xiaonan Prefecture.
يمتلك شياو شون محافظة شياونان.
But you…
لكن أنت...
What do you have?
ماذا لديك؟
I have you, who will risk his life for me.
أنا أملكك، أنت الذي سيخاطر بحياته من أجلي.
Two against two. I won't be scared.
اثنان ضد اثنين. لن أخاف.
Even if Xiao Xun interferes, we have Xiao Yu.
حتى لو تدخل شياو شون، فلدينا شياو يو.
Three against three, then.
ثلاثة ضد ثلاثة إذن.
Besides,
بجانب،
you can fight against not only two,
يمكنك القتال ضد أكثر من اثنين،
but even a hundred more.
بل وحتى مئة أخرى.
I want you to handle Deng Yi and Xie Yanfang.
أريدك أن تتعامل مع Deng Yi وXie Yanfang.
But Jiu, you look like you want to devour me.
لكن يا جيو، يبدو أنك تريد التهامني.
You should figure out
يجب أن تكتشف
how to handle Xiao Xun first.
كيفية التعامل مع شياو شون أولاً.
He suddenly proposed the sacrifice.
ثم اقترح التضحية فجأة.
He must have a plan.
لا بد أن لديه خطة.
I know.
أنا أعرف.
You know?
أنت تعرف؟
Then how can you remain so calm?
إذن كيف يمكنك أن تبقى هادئاً إلى هذا الحد؟
If I panicked, what would that change?
إذا شعرت بالذعر، فماذا سيتغير ذلك؟
I prefer to stay put and wait.
أفضّل البقاء في مكاني والانتظار.
I'll see how he's going to play his game.
سأرى كيف سيلعب لعبته.
Subtitle translation by:
ترجمة الترجمة الفرعية بواسطة: